All right. So, the best way I found to
teach while loops is typically to go
back and reference the if statement that
we learned when we were talking about
selection. So, let's say we have
something that we are trying to make a
guess about. So, uh or something we're
trying to check in this case. So, let's
say that we've got the user who's
entering in a password. So we'll say uh
let my pass let the entered
password equal prompt
what is the password
and then let's create just uh a
hard-coded password. We'll say let
correct password equal
um hello.
So when they've entered that prompt,
maybe we want to welcome them to the
system if they get the right password.
So we could say if the entered password
is exactly the same as the correct
password,
then
alert
welcome
to the system.
And then else
alert wrong password.
But wait a minute.
If they get the wrong password, we
probably do want to give them a second
attempt. I mean, can you imagine if you
tried to log in to your bank and you got
one attempt and if you ever got the
password wrong, you were never getting
in. That' probably be pretty bad. So,
you probably want to give them a couple
of attempts. Um, so I mean we could copy
the code
and paste it.
Man, generally you you get several
attempts. So we could copy the code and
paste it. But now we've copied and
pasted code. So what happens when we
need to change it from saying wrong
password to wrong password,
please try again. Now I'd have to change
it in every single spot that I just
copied it. And then sometimes, unlike a
password where you probably want to
limit the number of times someone can
attempt to enter the password, there are
some things that you want to keep going.
For example, let's say you are um
you're making a deposit into the bank
and you have a bunch of checks. I will
have no idea how many checks you have,
but I need the system to keep asking
you, do you want to deposit another
check while you still have checks? Um,
and that need to continually run
something over and over when we don't
know how many times to run it is why we
would use a while loop. So, I'm going to
show you how we could rewrite this
password logic to use a while loop so
we're not duplicating code. So, what I'm
going to do here is I'm going to use the
keyword while I'm going to say while the
entered password is not the same as the
correct password. And then I'm going to
put curly braces so I can have a code
block that will repeat. Anytime the
correct password and the enter password
are not the same, this code block will
repeat. So maybe we want to say, "Alert,
wrong password. Try again."
And then this will keep going until they
enter the right password. Some of you
may have noticed that there's a problem
with this code. Um,
but I like to demonstrate my computer
crashing. So, um, we're going to run
this anyway. Um,
okay. So, it says, "What is the
password?" And I'm going to type
gibberish. And I'm going to hit okay.
And it says, "Wrong password. Please try
again. Wrong password. Please try again.
Wrong password. Please try again." And
we are actually stuck in a never- ending
loop. a never- ending loop of being told
the wrong password because we've never
given ourselves a way to exit the loop.
If we come back over to our Visual
Studio Code, we said that the entered
password um as long as it was not the
same as the correct password, alert
this. But we never gave them a chance to
reenter their password. So, what we've
entered is what I like to call a really
long loop, but other people like to call
it an infinite loop. I have yet to see a
loop that's still running. So, you know,
that doesn't really meet the definition
of infinite for me, but technically
speaking, this is called an infinite
loop. Um, so we need this to stop. So,
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
kill my server and I'm going to come
over here and I'm going to kill the tab
and I'm going to come back over to
Visual Studio Code and I'm going to add
in a way for this loop to end. So, we're
going to say um entered password.
Uh, we'll So, if they're not the same,
then we need to alert them that it's the
wrong password. And then we'll say
entered password equals prompt.
Please try again.
So, now we'll save this. Now, there is a
way for our loop to end. Um, we don't
know how many times they'll enter the
wrong password cuz they could enter the
wrong password as many times as we want
and this while loop will keep running.
But as soon as they enter the right
password, meaning entered password and
correct password are equal, then this
condition is no longer true. And so it
will skip out of the while loop and the
while loop will end. So just to prove
that to you, oh, I'll need to hit my go
live button.
And it says, what is the password? And
I'll enter gibberish. And it says wrong
password. Please try again. What is the
password? Enter gibberish. Wrong
password. Please try again. Um, and then
it says, please try again. And here I'm
going to enter hello. and hit enter. And
the loop ended. Um, we were successfully
able to end the loop. So coming back
over to our Visual Studio Code, we can
see that this while loop will repeat as
long as this condition is met. And then
once it's done, then it will exit. So
the only way to exit this while loop
right now is if the enter password is
equal to the correct password. So what I
could do here is I could say alert
welcome
to the system
and then save that.
So if we come back over here it says
what is the password? Gibberish. Wrong
password. Please try again.
Wrong password. Please try again. Wrong
password. Please try again. Now we'll
enter the correct one and it'll say
welcome to the system. And so that is
how a while loop works. It evaluates a
condition just like an if statement
evaluates a condition. If the condition
is true, then it drops into the loop and
runs it and then it re-evaluates the
condition. And so as long as you've
created a way to exit the loop, then
there will be a way then you won't run
into infinite loops. So you always want
to make sure you've got a way to exit
your loop. Um this loop will continue to
run as long as the password's not the
same as the correct password. Once it is
the same, it'll exit and it'll alert
welcome to the system.